Chapter 42. The whiteness of the whale.
What the white whale was to Ahab has been hinted. What at times he was to me
as yet remains unsaid.
Aside from those more obvious considerations touching Moby Dick, which
could not but occasionally awaken in any man's soul some alarm, there was another
thought, or rather vague, nameless horror concerning him, which at times,
by its intensity, completely overpowered all the rest. And yet so mystical and
welln ineffable was it that I almost despair of putting it in a comprehensible form.
It was the whiteness of the whale that above all things appalled me. But how
can I hope to explain myself here and yet in some dim random way explain
myself I must else all these chapters might be not.
Though in many natural objects whiteness refiningly enhances beauty, as if
imparting some special virtue of its own, as in marbles, japonicas, and
pearls, and though various nations have in some ways recognized a certain royal
preeminence in this hue, even the barbaric grand old kings of Pegu placing
the title Lord of the White Elephants, above all their other magniloquent
ascriptions of dominion, and the modern kings of Syiam unfurling the same snow
white quadriped in the royal standard and the Hannavarian flag bearing the one
figure of a snow white charger and the great Austrian Empire Cesarian heir to
overlording Rome having for the imperial color the same imperial hue and though
this preeminence in it applies to the human race itself giving the white man
ideal masterership over every dusky tribe. And though besides all this,
whiteness has been even made significant of gladness, for among the Romans a
white stone marked a joyful day, and though in other mortal sympathies and
symbolizings, this same hue is made the emblem of many touching noble things,
the innocence of brides, the benignity of age, though among the red men of
America the giving of the white belt of wampom was the deepest pledge of honor.
Though in many clims whiteness typifies the majesty of justice in the man of the
judge and contributes to the daily state of kings and queens drawn by milk white
steeds. Though even in the higher mysteries of the most august religions,
it has been made the symbol of the divine spotlessness and power by the
Persian fire worshippers, the white forked flame being held the holiest on
the altar. And in the Greek mythologies, great Jo himself being made incarnate in
a snow white bull. And though to the noble Irakqua the mid-winter sacrifice
of the sacred white dog was by far the holiest festival of their theology, that
spotless faithful creature being held the purest envoy they could send to the
great spirit with the annual tidings of their own fidelity. And though directly
from the Latin word for white, all Christian priests derive the name of one
part of their sacred vesture, the alb or tunic worn beneath the cassak. And
though among the holy pomps of the Rish faith, white is specially employed in
the celebration of the passion of our Lord. Though in the vision of St. John,
white robes are given to the redeemed, and the four and 20 elders stand clothed
in white before the great white throne, and the holy one that siteth there white
like wool. Yet for all these accumulated associations with whatever is sweet and
honorable and sublime, there yet lurks an elusive something in the innermost
idea of this hue which strikes more of panic to the soul than that redness
which arrits in blood.
This elusive quality it is, which causes the thought of whiteness, when divorced
from more kindly associations, and coupled with any object terrible in
itself, to heighten that terror to the furthest bounds, witness the white bear
of the poles, and the white shark of the tropics. What but their smooth flaky
whiteness makes them the transcendent horrors they are. That ghastly whiteness
it is which imparts such an abhorent mildness even more loathsome than
terrific to the dumb gloating of their aspect. So that not the fierce fanged
tiger in his heraldic coat can so stagger courage as the white shrouded bear or shark.
Footnote with reference to the polar bear. It may possibly be urged by him
who would fain go still deeper into this matter, that it is not the whiteness
separately regarded which heightens the intolerable hideousness of that brute.
For analyzed that heightened hideousness, it might be said, only
rises from the circumstance that the irresponsible ferociousness of the
creature stands invested in the fleece of celestial innocence and love. And
hence, by bringing together two such opposite emotions in our minds, the
polar bear frightens us with so unnatural a contrast. But even assuming
all this to be true, yet were it not for the whiteness, he would not have that
intensified terror.
As for the white shark, the white gliding ghostliness of repose in that
creature when beheld in his ordinary moods strangely tallies with the same
quality in the polar quadriped.
This peculiarity is most vividly hit by the French in the name they bestow upon
that fish. The Romeish mass for the dead begins with Reququiam eternum eternal
rest whence Reququum denominating the mass itself and any other funeral music.
Now in all to the white silent stillness of death in this shark and the mild
deadliness of his habits, the French call him Raheen.
End of footnote.
Beth think thee of the albatross. Whence come those clouds of spiritual
wonderment and pale dread in which that white phantom sails in all imaginations.
Not Cridge first through that spell, but God's great unflattering laurate nature.
Footnote. I remember the first albatross I ever saw. It was during a prolonged
gale in waters hard upon the Antarctic seas. From my for noon watch below, I
ascended to the overclouded deck, and there dashed upon the main hatches, I
saw a regal, feathery thing of unspotted whiteness, and with a hooked Roman bill
sublime. At intervals it arched forth its vast archangel wings, as if to
embrace some holy ark. Wondrous flutterings and throbbings shook it.
Though bodily unharmed, it uttered cries as some king's ghost in supernatural
distress. Through its inexpressable, strange eyes, me thought I peeped to
secrets which took hold of God. As Abraham before the angels I bowed
myself, the white thing was so white, its wings so wide, and in those forever
exiled waters, I had lost the miserable warping memories of traditions and of
towns. Long I gazed at that prodigy of plumage. I cannot tell, can only hint
the things that darted through me then.
But at last I awoke, and turning asked a sailor, "What bird was this?" "A goni,"
he replied. "Gon. Never had heard that name before. Is it conceivable that this
glorious thing is utterly unknown to men ashore?" "Never." But sometime after I
learned that Goon was some seaman's name for albatross, so that by no possibility
could Cridge's wild rhyme have had ought to do with those mystical impressions
which were mine when I saw that bird upon our deck. For neither had I then
read the rhyme, nor knew the bird to be an albatross. Yet in saying this I do
but indirectly burnish a little brighter the noble merit of the poem and the
poet. I assert then that in the wondrous bodily whiteness of the bird chiefly
lurks the secret of the spell, a truth more evinced in this, that by a solicism
of terms there are birds called gray albatrosses, and these I have frequently
seen, but never with such emotions as when I beheld the Antarctic fowl. But
how had the mystic thing been caught?
Whisper it not, and I will tell. with a treacherous hook and line as the fowl
floated on the sea. At last the captain made a postman of it, tying a lettered
leather tally around its neck with the ship's time and place and then letting
it escape. But I doubt not that leather tally meant for man was taken off in
heaven when the white fowl flew to join the wingfolding, the invoking and adoring carob beam.
End of footnote.
Most famous in our western annals and Indian traditions is that of the white
steed of the prairies. A magnificent milkweight charger, largeeyed,
smallheaded, bluffchested, and with the dignity of a thousand monarchs in his
lofty, overscorning carriage. He was the elected Xerxes of vast herds of wild
horses whose pastures in those days were only fenced by the Rocky Mountains and
the Alaganes. At their flaming head he westward trooped it like that chosen
star which every evening leads on the hosts of light. The flashing cascade of
his man, the curving comet of his tail, invested him with housings more
respplendant than gold and silverbeers could have furnished him. a most
imperial and archangelical apparition of that unfallen western world, which to
the eyes of the old trappers and hunters revived the glories of those primeval
times, when Adam walked majestic as a god, bluff browed and fearless as this
mighty steed, whether marching amid his aids and marshals in the van of
countless cohorts that endlessly streamed it over the plains like an
Ohio, or whether with his circum ambient subjects browsing all around at the
horizon. The white steed gallopingly reviewed them with warm nostrils reening
through his cool milkiness. In whatever aspect he presented himself always to
the bravest Indians he was the object of trembling reverence and awe. Nor can it
be questioned from what stands on legendary record of this noble horse,
that it was his spiritual whiteness chiefly which so clothed him with
diviness, and that this divess had that in it which, though commanding worship,
at the same time enforced a certain nameless terror.
But there are other instances where this whiteness loses all that accessory and
strange glory which invests it in the white steed in albatross.
What is it that in the albino man so peculiarly repels and often shocks the
eye as that sometimes he is loathed by his own kith and kin. It is that
whiteness which invests him, a thing expressed by the name he bears. The
albino is as well-made as other men, has no substantive deformity, and yet this
mere aspect of all pervading whiteness makes him more strangely hideous than
the ugliest abortion. Why should this be so? Nor in quite other aspects does
nature, in her least palpable, but not the less malicious agencies, fail to
enlist among her forces this crowning attribute of the terrible. From its
snowy aspect, the gauntleted ghost of the southern seas has been denominated
the white squall. Nor in some historic instances has the art of human malice
omitted so potent an auxiliary. How wildly it heightens the effect of that
passage in Frasar, when masked in the snowy symbol of their faction, the
desperate white hoods of Gent murder their baiff in the marketplace.
Nor in some things does the common hereditary experience of all mankind
fail to bear witness to the supernaturalism of this hue. It cannot
well be doubted that the one visible quality in the aspect of the dead which
most appalls the gazer is the marble power lingering there. As if indeed that
power were as much like the badge of consternation in the other world as of
mortal trepidation here. And from that pour of the dead we borrow the
expressive hue of the shroud in which we wrapped them. Nor even in our
superstitions do we fail to throw the same snowy mantle around our phantoms.
All ghosts rising in a milk white fog.
Yay, while these terrors seize us, let us add that even the king of terrors
when personified by the evangelist rides on his palid horse.
Therefore, in his other moods symbolize whatever grand or gracious thing he will
by whiteness, no man can deny that in its profoundest idealized significance
it calls up a peculiar apparition to the soul.
But though without disscent this point be fixed, how is mortal man to account
for it? To analyze it would seem impossible.
Can we then by the citation of some of those instances, wherein this thing of
whiteness, though for the time, either wholly or in great part stripped of all
direct associations calculated to impart to it ought fearful, but nevertheless is
found to exert over us the same sorcery, however modified, can we thus hope to
light upon some chance clue to conduct us to the hidden cause we seek? Let us
try. But in a matter like this, subtlety appeals to subtlety, and without
imagination, no man can follow another into these halls. And though doubtless
some, at least of the imaginative impressions about to be presented, may
have been shared by most men, yet few perhaps were entirely conscious of them
at the time, and therefore may not be able to recall them now.
Why, to the man of untutoed ideality, who happens to be but loosely acquainted
with the peculiar character of the day, does the bare mention of wits and tide
marshall in the fancy such long, dreary, speechless processions of slowpacing
pilgrims, downcast and hooden with new fallen snow? or to the unread,
unsophisticated Protestant of Middle American states, why does the passing
mention of a white frier or a white nun evoke such an eyeless statue in the soul?
Or what is there apart from the traditions of dungeoned warriors and
kings which will not wholly account for it that makes the White Tower of London
tell so much more strongly on the imagination of an untraveled American
than those other storied structures its neighbors the byword tower or even the
bloody and those sublimer towers the white mountains of New Hampshire whence
in peculiar moods comes that gigantic ghostliness over for the soul at the
bare mention of that name, while the thought of Virginia's Blue Ridge is full
of a soft, dewy, distant dreaminess. Or why, irrespective of all latitudes and
longitudes, does the name of the White Sea exert such a spectralness over the
fancy, while that of the Yellow Sea lulls us with mortal thoughts of long,
lacquered, mild afternoons on the waves, followed by the gaudiest and yet
sleepiest of sunsets, or to choose a wholly unsubstantial instance, purely
addressed to the fancy, why, in reading the old fairy tales of central Central
Europe does the tall pale man of the heart's forests, whose changeless power
unrustlingly glides through the green of the groves, why is this phantom more
terrible than all the whooping imps of the Bloxburg?
Nor is it altogether the remembrance of her cathedral toppling earthquakes, nor
the stampedes of her frantic seas, nor the tearlessness of arid skies that
never rain, nor the sight of her wide field of leaning spires, wrenched
copstones and crosses all a droop like caned yards of anchored fleets, and her
suburban avenues of house walls lying upon each other as a tossed pack of
cards. It is not these things alone which make tearless Lima the strangest,
saddest city thou can see. For Lima has taken the white veil, and there is a
higher horror in this whiteness of her woe. Old as Pizarro, this whiteness
keeps her ruins forever new. admits not the cheerful greenness of complete
decay, spreads over her broken ramparts the rigid power of an apoplelexy that
fixes its own distortions.
I know that to the common apprehension, this phenomenon of whiteness is not
confessed to be the prime agent in exaggerating the terror of objects
otherwise terrible. Nor to the unimaginative mind is there ought of
terror in those appearances whose awfulness to another mind almost solely
consists in this one phenomenon, especially when exhibited under any form
at all approaching to muteness or universality.
What I mean by these two statements may perhaps be respectively elucidated by
the following examples.
First the mariner, when drawing nigh the coasts of foreign lands, if by night he
hear the roar of breakers, starts to vigilance, and feels just enough of
trepidation to sharpen all his faculties. But under precisely similar
circumstances, let him be called from his hammock to view his ship sailing
through a midnight sea of milky whiteness, as if from encircling
headlands, shors of combed white bears were swimming around him. Then he feels
a silent superstitious dread. The shrouded phantom of the whitened waters
is horrible to him as a real ghost. In vain, the lead assures him he is still
off soundings. part and helm they both go down. He never rests till blue water
is under him again. Yet where is the mariner who will tell thee, "Sir, it was
not so much the fear of striking hidden rocks as the fear of that hideous
whiteness that so stirred me."
Second, to the native Indian of Peru, the continual sight of the snow how
ahead Andes conveys not of dread, except perhaps in the mere fancing of the
eternal frosted desolateness reigning at such vast altitudes, and the natural
conceit of what a fearfulness it would be to lose oneself in such inhuman solitudes.
Much the same is it with the backwoodsman of the West, who with
comparative indifference views an unbounded prairie sheetated with driven
snow, no shadow of tree or twig to break the fixed trance of whiteness. Not so
the sailor, beholding the scenery of the Antarctic seas, where at times, by some
infernal trick of leisure domain in the powers of frost and air, he, shivering
and half shipwrecked, instead of rainbows speaking hope and solace to his
misery, views what seems a boundless churchyard grinning upon him with its
lean ice monuments and splintered crosses.
But thou sayest me thinks that white chapter about whiteness is but a white
flag hung out from a craven soul. Thou surrenderest to a hypo Ishmael.
Tell me why this strong young cult fold in some peaceful valley of Vermont far
removed from all beasts of prey. Why is it that upon the sunniest day, if you
but shake a fresh buffalo robe behind him, so that he cannot even see it, but
only smells its wild animal muskiness, why will he start, snort, and with
bursting eyes paw the ground in frenzies of a fright? There is no remembrance in
him of any gorings of wild creatures in his green northern home, so that the
strange muskiness he smells cannot recall to him anything associated with
the experience of former perils. For what knows he this New England cult of
the black bisons of distant Oregon?
No, but here thou beholdest even in a dumb brute the instinct of the knowledge
of the demonism in the world. Though thousands of miles from Oregon, still
when he smells that savage musk, the rending goring bison herds are as
present as to the deserted wild fo of the prairies, which in this instant they
may be trampling into dust.
Thus then, the muffled rollings of a milky sea, the bleak rustlings of the
feson frosts of mountains, the desolate shiftings of the windroad snows of
prairies, all these to Ishmael are as the shaking of that buffalo robe to the
frightened colt. Though neither knows where lie the nameless things of which
the mystic sign gives forth such hints, yet with me, as with the cult, somewhere
those things must exist, though in many of its aspects this visible world seems
formed in love. The invisible spheres were formed in fright.
But not yet have we solved the incantation of this whiteness and
learned why it appeals with such power to the soul and more strange and far
more portentious. Why, as we have seen, it is at once the most meaning symbol of
spiritual things, nay the very veil of the Christian deity, and yet should be
as it is the intensifying agent in things most appalling to mankind.
Is it that by its indefinitess it shadows forth the heartless voids and
immensities of the universe and thus stabs us from behind with the thought of
annihilation when beholding the white depths of the Milky Way? Or is it that
as in essence whiteness is not so much a color as the visible absence of color
and at the same time the concrete of all colors. Is it for these reasons that
there is such a dumb blankness full of meaning in a wide landscape of snows a
colorless all color of atheism from which we shrink. And when we consider
that other theory of the natural philosophers that all other earthly
hues, every stately or lovely emlazing, the sweet tinges of sunset skies and
woods, yay, the gilded velvets of butterflies, and the butterfly cheeks of
young girls, all these are but subtle deceits, not actually inherent in
substances, but only laid on from without, so that all deified nature
absolutely paints like a harlot whose allurements cover nothing but the charal
house within. And when we proceed further and consider that the mystical
cosmetic which produces every one of her hues, the great principle of light
forever remains white or colorless in itself, and if operating without medium
upon matter, would touch all objects, even tulips and roses, with its own
blank tinge. Pondering all this, the Paulied universe lies before us a leper,
and like willful travelers in Lapland, who refuse to wear colored and coloring
glasses upon their eyes, so the wretched infidel gazes himself blind at the
monumental white shroud that wraps all the prospect around him. And of all
these things, the albino whale was the symbol.
Wonder ye then at the fiery hunt.